Guide to the Betsy Wade Files on the Newspaper Guild of New York WAG.045
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Betsy Wade Files on the Newspaper Guild of New York
1966-1984
WAG.045
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
6.0 linear feet in 6 record cartons.
Wade, Betsy
Box 1-6
Historical/Biographical Note
The Newspaper Guild was founded December 15, 1933; journalist Heywood Broun was its first president. In New York, the Guild's first contract was negotiated with the New York Post in 1935. The Guild, which includes locals in Canada and Puerto Rico, as well as throughout the United States, called itself the American Newspaper Guild (ANG) until 1971, when it changed its name to the present The Newspaper Guild (TNG). From the mid-1970's to the mid-1980's (the period covered by the Papers, with the exception of some material from 1967) Local 3 membership stood at roughly 5,000 and the International at about 30,000.
Wade was nominated by petition both times she ran for the presidency of Local 3 (as-opposed to the union's more usual procedure in which a candidate is nominated by the local's Representative Assembly by a quorum of member representing a certain number of shops). Her election to her second term (which began in 1980) was challenged by the losing candidates, who forced a re-run of the election (supervised by the Department of Labor) in September 1982. Wade did not run for president in this election re-run; instead she ran for membership on the Local's Executive Committee. She and all the members of her insurgent Membership Slate were defeated in this election. In December 1982 Wade also ran unsuccessfully for the office of Local Executive Vice President.
Wade also served three times as a regional president of the Guild's International. She ran unopposed for her first term (as was usual in elections for this position), but the elections for her next two terms were contested.
Arrangement
While the Papers have not been arranged in their original order, a heavy reliance has been placed on the organization and dating of the original collection and on the subject designations given to materials by Wade and Mecham.
The collection has been divided into five series (The Newspaper Guild, Local 3, District Councils, Foreign Affairs, and Other Newspaper Unions, respectively), and numerous subseries. Series are designated by Roman numerals, subseries by Arabic numbers. Subseries are generally arranged in the following order of priority: lists of officers or members, general correspondence, parts of organizational bodies (such as executive committees or units), then subject (such as bargaining or organizing) and/or form (such as petitions or campaign literature), arranged in alphabetical order. All documents are arranged in chronological order within folders, with undated materials at the back of the last folder of a subdivision. Within Local Executive Committee and International Executive Board subseries, subcommittees are arranged in alphabetical order; unit subseries are also arranged in alphabetical order by unit.
Except where exceptions are noted, dates on the container list refer to the dates of the documents in a folder. They represent only ranges not complete records or runs. That is, a folder dated 1976-1979 will not necessarily have all the relevant documents for those years-the marking only signifies that documents in that folder fall into that range of dates. If, however, there is only one or a very small number of documents from a particular year in a folder with a larger number from another year or range of years, it is usually represented like this: 1967; 1975-1979, rather than including it in the date range as 1967-1979.
Drafts of documents are filed with finished documents unless there is a large or significant enough group of drafts to justify a separate subdivision or folder.
When there are types of documents distinct enough in form from one another (for example, correspondence and contracts) within the same folder, they may be arranged first by form, and then chronologically within form.
Scope and Content
It is important to note first what these Papers are not. They are not the official files of the Newspaper Guild nor of Local 3 (the Papers' organizational records of Local 3 and TNG are fragmentary and incomplete), nor are they the personal papers of Betsy Wade, although they incorporate elements of both. They are, instead, Betsy Wade's personal collection of records of and relating to the Newspaper Guild and its Local 3-mostly in the periods from 1975 to 1984-and materials given to Wade by Rose Mary Mechem that relate to the Guild's policies regarding involvement in (United States) government-supported or government-sponsored organizations and programs in Latin American and elsewhere abroad.
The focus of most of these documents is on the activities of Wade and an "insurgent caucus" with which she was associated in the International and in Local 3. These materials document a lively struggle between the insurgents and their supporters (variously called the Reponsibility Slate, the Membership Slate, etc.) and the insurgents' opponents (different individuals and slates variously called the Democratic Coalition, the Representative Assembly Slate, the Unity Slate, etc.) at every level of the organization and on practically every issue.
Throughout the collection-which covers a fairly broad spectrum of Guild concerns and activities, and in which are represented all levels of the organization-this conflict is evident. But nowhere is it better or more clearly illustrated than in the group of materials concerned with elections and referenda (Series II, subseries 10, "Elections, Referenda, Disputes"). Here are gathered materials on more than twenty-five elections, referenda and public disputes that took place in Local 3 in the years from 1978 to 1984. These materials (largely, though not entirely, campaign literature), which amount to over one-third of the collection form the heart of the Papers, for it is here that the most concentrated, chronological picture of the issues and personalities at the core of the conflicts may be seen.
Another group of materials in the Papers, however, concentrates on one particular aspect of these conflicts: disagreements at the Guild-wide level over Guild involvement in government-supported or government-sponsored programs in foreign countries. Series IV (Foreign Affairs) documents the struggle, within the Guild over this issue, which began as early as 1967, with revelations of CIA involvement in the American Institute for Free Labor Development (AIFLD) that resulted in the termination of TNG-AIFLD joint programs, and re-emerged in the late 1970's and early 1980's with the resumption of these programs. Much of this material is drawn from documents gathered by Rose Mary Mechem and given to Betsy Wade, although a significant amount also comes from Wade, who also collected materials on the subject.
While, as had been said, the focus of the Papers is on the internal struggle in the Guild, the collection is also a good source of information on a broader range of concerns that have to do with the administration and activities of a labor union. the minutes of the International Executive Board of TNG, of the Executive Committee of Local 3, and the Representative Assembly and General Membership Meeting of Local 3 are particularly useful in this regard. While these by no means represent complete runs of all the years indicated, some are close to complete.
Also of particular value, and interfiled throughout the collection, are handwritten notes. Some of these are merely marginal notations written directly onto various documents (such as meeting agendas) that record, for example, whether Wade attended a particular meeting or when and how many copies of a leaflet were distributed. Others, however, are far more extensive: personal minutes, for example, of meetings, and notes on telephone conversations, with some dialog recorded verbatim. On occasion these notes are separate individual documents, but more often they are written on the front or back of preexisting documents such as leaflets. For this reason the researcher should take care to examine both sides of all documents in the Papers. Most of these notes appear to be in Wade's hand. A sample of Wade's handwriting is included in the appendices, to assist the researcher in making this determination.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donor sent a gift of 11 boxes of files documenting the Newspaper Guild and the Newspaper Guild of New York involvement of Betsy Wade and insurgent caucus from 1975-1984 in May 1986. The accession number associated with this gift is 1995.004.
Separated Materials
Photographs were separated from this collection during initial processing and were established as a separate collection, the Betsy Wade Photographs (PHOTOS 040).
- Lists of Officers, National and Local, 1977-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Convention Delegates List, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Guild Reporter (1 item), not dated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Locals, Miscellaneous Documents, various dates (Box 1, Folder 4)
- General Correspondence (1 of 2), 1974;1975;1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- General Correspondence (2 of 2), 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Strike Benefits-Correspondence/Memos, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- (Locals) Good Standing Data, 1979; 1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- International Executive Board ("I.E.B."): Correspondence and Notes, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- International Executive Board: Policy Statements/Resolutions/Recommendations, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- International Executive Board: Rules, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- International Executive Board: Committee Membership Lists, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- International Executive Board: Appeals Committee: Report, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- International Executive Board: Collective Bargaining Committee: Strike Newspaper Documents, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- International Executive Board: Constitution Committee: Report and Memo, 1976 and 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- International Executive Board: Contracts Committee: Reports, January 20, 1976-April 22, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- International Executive Board: Contracts Committee: Contract Reports (Summary Analyses), A through W, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- International Executive Board: Finance and Administration Committee: Reports and Motions, 1976-1982 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- International Executive Board?-The Newspaper Guild Budgets/Finances, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- International Executive Board: Human Rights Committee: Memo/Report, 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- International Executive Board: Human Rights Committee: Discrimination Caselogs (Equal Employment Opportunity Commission), January, April 1981 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Human Rights: Analyses of Guild Locals by Race, Ethnic Origins, and Sex (Statistics), not dated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- International Executive Board: Special Defense Fund Committee: Report, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- International Executive Board: Minutes (1 of 6), October 1975-June 1976 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- International Executive Board: Minutes (2 of 6), October 1976-July 1977 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- International Executive Board: Minutes (3 of 6), October 1977-October 1978 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- International Executive Board: Minutes (4 of 6), April 1979-April 1980 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- International Executive Board: Minutes, agendas and notes (5 of 6), June 20, 1980-January 29, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- International Executive Board: Minutes, agendas and notes (6 of 6), April 27, 1981-January 25-January 26, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Reports on International Executive Board: Meetings to Local 3 Executive Committee, 1975-1981 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Reports on International Executive Board Meetings by Regional Vice Presidents, 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Board of Trustees of the Newspaper Guild Commingled Pension Trust: Investment Guidelines, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Special Merger Committee, 1979-1980; 1982 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Administrative Manual (fragments), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Arbitration Awards, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- List of Arbitrators, not dated (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Contract Index, November 1981 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Collective Bargaining Manual 1 (Minimum Salaries/Salary Comparisons), ca. 1982 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Collective Bargaining Manual 2 (Guild contract provisions, dues check off, mileage rates), ca. 1982 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Pension Plans (summary), January 1983 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Bargaining and Strike Rules, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Organizing-Local 3-Various Units/Newspapers, New York City: Memos, Correspondence, Leaflets, 1976-1982 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Organizing-Local 3-New Haven drive: Memos, Leaflets, Membership List, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Organizing-Local 10, Philadelphia Evening Bulletin; Memos, Correspondence, Leaflets, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Organizing-Local 10, Philadelphia Evening Bulletin: Management memos, Correspondence, Leaflets, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Organizing-Local 10, Philadelphia Evening Bulletin: National Labor Relations Board Decision, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Organizing-Local 35 (Washington D.C.-Baltimore: Leaflets, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Organizing-General Materials: Checklist, Manual, Leaflets, Statements, 1975-1981 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Organizing-Management Anti-Organizing Literature, 1977 and not dated (Box 1, Folder 49)
- International Election and Referendum Committee: Report and Rules, October 1979-August 1981 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Unit Clarification: Decisions-Salem (Massachusetts) Publishing Co.; Columbus (Ohio) Dispatch; Eugene (Oregon) Register-Guard, 1972; 1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Unit Clarification: Petitions-The Newspaper Guild National Conference on Unit Clarification Petitions Program/Kit, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Women's Meeting (Detroit Convention): Correspondence, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Unit Officers, Represntative Assembly Members, and Other Members: Lists and Mailing Lists, 1976-1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Committees, Delegates: Appointments and Membership Lists, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- General Correspondence (1 of 6), 1974-1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- General Correspondence (2 of 6), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- General Correspondence (3 of 6), 1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- General Correspondence (4 of 6), 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- General Correspondence (5 of 6), 1982 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- General Correspondence (6 of 6) (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Strike Benefits Correspondence and Memos, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Executive Committee: Agendas, minutes and motions (1 of 7), September 21, 1979-June 19, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Executive Committee: Agendas, minutes and motions (2 of 7), July 10, 1979-May 14, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Executive Committee: Agendas, minutes and motions (3 of 7), May 20, 1980-November 18, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Executive Committee: Agendas, minutes and motions (4 of 7), December 4, 1980-July 21, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Executive Committee: Agendas, minutes and motions (5 of 7), August 11, 1981-January 28, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Executive Committee: Agendas, minutes and motions (6 of 7), February 9, 1982-January 18, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Executive Committee: Agendas, minutes and motions (7 of 7), February 15, 1983-October 25, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Executive Committee: Correspondence and Reports, 1979-1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Executive Committee: Rules (Drafts), 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Ad Hoc Committees, A to Z, 1979-1982 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Administrative Committee: Memos, meeting notices, agenda/minutes, 1979-1982 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Contract Enforcement Committee: Meeting notices, agendas, memos, 1978-1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Elections Committee: Meeting notices, minutes and correspondence, 1979-1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Finance Committee: Meeting notices, agendas, correspondence, recommendations and notions, reports, 1979-1982 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Frontpage, Education and Publicity Committee: Meeting notices, agendas, correspondence, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Headquarters Committee: Meeting notices, memos, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Human Rights Committee: meeting notices, memos, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Membership and Shop Stewards Committee: Meeting notices, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Open Shop/Magazines Committee: Minutes, meeting notices, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Organizing Committee: Meeting notices, memos, 1979-1982 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Page One Awards: Meeting notices, memos, press releases, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Trial Board: Minutes, reports, hearing transcripts, rules, 1979-1982 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Trial Board: Correspondence/memos, decisions, meeting notices, 1979-1982 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- General Membership Meeting: Reports/Minutes, March 6, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- General Membership Meeting: Announcements, agendas, minutes, 1978-1984 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- General Membership Meeting: President's reports/speeches, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Representative Assembly: Agendas and minutes, memos, reports, motions, President's speech (1 of 5), October 27, 1976-September 27, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Representative Assembly: Agendas and minutes, memos, reports, motions (2 of 5), October 31, 1979-April 23, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Representative Assembly: Meeting agenda and transcript (3 of 5), June 18, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Representative Assembly: Minutes, agendas, and reports (4 of 5), September 24, 1980-December 16, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Representative Assembly: Agendas, minutes, reports (5 of 5), January 27, 1982-October 31, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Amsterdam News unit: Leaflets and correspondence, 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Consumers Union unit: Correspondence, negotiations report, 1979-1981 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Daily News unit: Discrimination complaints to Equal Employment Oppportunity Commission, EEOC petitions, affidavits to United States District Court, and EEOC determination, 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Daily News unit: Correspondence, documents (of management, union and other organizations) relating to proposed sale of Daily News, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Daily News unit: Union responses to proposed sale of Daily News, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Daily News unit: Unit clarification notes, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Daily World unit: Correspondence, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- The Home News unit (New Brunswick, New Jersey): Correspondence, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- New York Times unit: Correspondence, 1978-1982 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- New York Times unit: Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- New York Times unit: Negotiated descriptions of Guild jobs at the New York Times, not dated (Box 4, Folder 11)
- New York Times unit-Guild Times Pension, Welfare, Scholarship Fund: Correspondence, reports, agendas, 1981-1985 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- New York Times unit: Pension Plan text, ca. 1976 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- New York Times unit-Rosario Case (Minorities class action suit against the New York Times): Litigation documents and related information, 1979-1981 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- New York Times unit: Union Times drafts, with notes on distribution, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Reuters unit: Correspondence, memos, petition, 1978-1984 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Standard and Poor's unit: Sex discrimination complaints, 1977 and 1980 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Time Inc. unit: Correspondence, leaflets, 1980-1984 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Waterbury American-Republican unit: Correspondence, survey, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Wire Service Guild: Officer list, correspondence, petition to National Labor Regulations Board, 1979-1982; not dated (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Daily News: union and management contract proposals, memoranda of agreement, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Daily News: contract and buyout proposal, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- New York Post: Report, memos, contract language, complaint to National Labor Regualtion Board, 1978-1981 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- New York Times: Correspondence/Memos, notes, 1982-1984 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- New York Times: Severance pay provisions, contract language, memos/correspondence, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- New York Times: Contract proposals/language, memos, correspondence, notes, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- New York Times: Unfair labor practice charges, statements, and National Labor Regulation Board rulings on, 1979 and 1983 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- New York Times: Dual minimum notes, correspondence, memoranda and letters of agreement, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- (Mostly) New York Times: Memos, planning, contract proposals, memoranda of agreement, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- (Mostly) New York Times: Memos, contract proposals, memoranda of agreement, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- (Mostly) New York Times: Management leaflets, memo, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 31)
- New York Times: Galleys of contract, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 32)
- New York Times: Memorandum of agreement, memoranda of agreement drafts and amendments, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 33)
- New York Times: Unit clarification negotiation notes and correspondence/memos, 1979-1984 (Box 4, Folder 34)
- New York Times: Unit clarification settlement agreement and amendments; New York Times unit clarification petition to National Labor Regulation Board amendments, 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 35)
- New York Times: Arbitration award, 1979;1982 (Box 4, Folder 36)
- Contracts (by unit, A-Z), contracts in negotiation, proposed contracts, 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Private bargaining agents: Shadlen correspondence, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 38)
- Consolidated Unions Research Efforts Trust: Correspondence, Contracts, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 39)
- Local election: Responsibility State leaflets, December 1978 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Local election: Drafts of Responsibility Slate campaign literature and drafts of news/stories, December 1978 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Local election: Representative Assembly Slate-leaflets, December 1978 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Local election: Miscellaneous leaflets, Decmber 1978 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Local election: Responsibility Slate-correspondence, December 1978 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Local election: Responsibility Slate-campaign notes and strategies, December 1978 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Local election: Responsibility Slate-financial records, December 1978 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- By-election: Leaflets, April 1979 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- International Executive Board election: Campaign leaflets for Pat Vallila and anti-Open Choice Slate leaflets, September 1979 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- International Executive Board election: Committee for an Open-Choice-leaflets, September 1979 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- International Executive Board election: Committee for an Open Choice-drafts of campaign literature and campaign art work, September 1979 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- International Executive Board election: Committee for an Open Choice/Committee to Re-Elect Betsy Wade-financial reports, September 1979 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- International Executive Board election: Committee for an Open Choice-correspondence, September 1979 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- International Executive Board election: Committee for an Open Choice-campaign notes and memos, September 1979 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- (New York Times) Unit Referendum on pension allocation: leaflets, September 1979 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- (New York Times) Unit election for delegates to Representative Assembly-leaflets, January 1980 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- The Newspaper Guild convention delegates election: Membership Slate and allies' leaflets, May 1980 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- The Newspaper Guild convention delegates election: Membership Slate-correspondence, May 1980 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- The Newspaper Guild convention delegates election: Membership Slate-notes and financial records, May 1980 (Box 5, Folder 19)